Finding Aid for Albert Joseph Engel Papers 1885-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert Joseph Engel Papers 1885-1960
Engel, Albert Joseph, 1888-1959.
Prosecuting attorney for Missaukee County, Michigan, Republican State Senator, and U.S. Congressman from the 9th Michigan District from 1935 to 1951. Correspondence, reports and newspaper clippings concerning his activities on the House Appropriations Subcommittee on the Armed Services; material on the Manhattan Project and the testing of the atomic and hydrogen bombs; and photographs.
851419 Aa 2
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Albert J. Engel, Jr., (donor 4690 ) in 1968.
The collection is open for research.
The 16mm films in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles and high resolution digital files of some titles were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
Albert J. Engel was born in New Washington, Ohio on January 1, 1888. He graduated from the law department of Northwestern University in 1910. He then was admitted to the bar and commenced the practice of law in Lake City, Michigan. He was prosecuting attorney of Missaukee County in 1916-1917 and 1919-1920. During the first World War, Engel served as a first lieutenant in the War Department, later promoted to captain where he served overseas for twenty-three months, 1917-1919.
Engel served four terms in the state senate 1921 and 1927-1931. He was elected to the U.S. Congress in 1934 from Michigan's Ninth District. He came to serve eight terms, from 1935 to 1951. While in the congress, Engel served ten years as a member and chairman of the House Armed Forces appropriations subcommittee. In 1943, he began a one-man investigation of Army waste in which he traveled about the country touring army bases. Upon his return Engel proposed reforms which saved the government billions of dollars. He did not seek reelection in 1950 but rather sought (without success) the Republican nomination for governor. In his retirement, Engel operated a Christmas tree plantation near Lake City. He died December 2, 1959.
The Albert J. Engel papers primarily document his eight terms of service in United States House of Representatives, 1935-1951, though is some correspondence and other material dating back to 1911. The papers include correspondence, speeches, press releases, clippings scrapbooks and articles about Engel, files on various topics that came before Engel's House committees -- notably the Bikini Island A bomb and H bomb tests, and photographs
Subjects:
Atomic bomb.; Elections--Michigan--1950.; Engel, Albert Joseph, 1888-1959.; Hydrogen bomb.; Lake City (Mich.); Lawyers--Michigan.; Manhattan Project (U.S.); Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Missaukee County (Mich.); Politicians--Michigan--Missaukee County.; Presidents--United States--Election--1928.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Congress. House.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1923-1929.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Engel, Albert Joseph, 1888-1959.; France.; Iran.; Israel.; Italy.; Military art and science.; Politics and government--1946-1960.; United States. Congress. House.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.
Contributors:
Adams, James Truslow, 1878-1949.; Baer, Max A.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966.; Carlson, Frank, 1893-1987; Connally, Tom, 1877-1963.; Curwood, James Oliver, 1878-1927.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Disney, Walt, 1901-1966.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Forrestal, James, 1892-1949.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; Hannah, John A., 1902-1991; Hare, James M. (James McNeil), 1910-1980; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987.; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969.; Lubin, Isador, 1896-1978; McLaughlin, James Campbell, 1858-1932.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959.; Martin, Joseph William, 1884-1968.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988.; Patterson, Robert Porter, 1891-1952.; Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Powers, Perry Francis, 1857-1945.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Sparks, Frank Melville, 1877-; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950.; Symington, Stuart, 1901-1988; Thompson, Ruth, 1887-1970.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Townsend, Francis E. (Francis Everett), 1867-1960.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Tunney, James Joseph, 1897-; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1883-1953.; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Postcards.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes letters from fellow members of Congress, cabinet officers, Michigan political figures and some constituent mail. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. A select index to correspondents lists letters from some of the more prominent individuals represented in the series.
  - Undated, 1911-1948, 25 folders (Box 1)
  - 1949-1960, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - re A.J. Engel Oil Co. 1935-1943, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Papers (financial and political)
  - Undated 1885-1960, 9 folders (Box 2)
- Congressional Papers
  The Congressional Papers series consists of subject files, speeches, press releases and articles written by Engel. The subject files relate to topics which came before the House Appropriations Subcommittee on the Armed Services, including the 1946 atomic and hydrogen bomb tests on Bikini Island.
  - James Couzens Memorial Fund 1937 (Box 3)
  - German air power 1937 (Box 3)
  - Overseas trips 1945, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Bikini Island A bomb test 1946 (Box 3)
  - Bikini Island H bomb test 1946 (Box 3)
  - Air Transport Command in the Pacific 1945, undated (Box 3)
  - Panamint Press (newspaper published aboard the USS Panamint during the time of the atom bomb tests) (Box 3)
  - Panamint Parade (Box 3)
  - Speeches 1939-1950, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Press releases 1941 (Box 3)
  - Articles written by AJE (Box 3)
  - Notebooks regarding production of ammunition, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Notebook containing mailing lists and lists of supporters (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  - Clippings from Congressional Record
    - 1936-1939 (Box 4)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 4)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 4)
    - 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    - 1947 (Box 4)
    - 1948 (Box 4)
  - Arranged by date
    - 1931-1941, 4 volumes; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - 1941-1946, 4 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1947-1950, 2 volumes (Box 7)
  - Album of Washington memorabilia 1930s-1940s (Box 7)
  - Clippings (loose)
    - 1930s-1950s (Box 8)
- Visual Materials
  The visual materials series consists of photographs and a single motion picture. The photographs include portraits of Engel, his family and friends; pictures from his political campaigns, and his photos from his 1945 trip investigating waste at military bases around the world. The motion picture also documents that investigation.
  - Photographs
    - Campaigns (Box 9)
    - Europe (Italy) circa 1945 (Box 9)
    - Family and friends, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - France circa 1918 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Near East (Iran, Egypt, Palestine) circa 1945 (Box 9)
    - Portraits (Box 9)
    - South Pacific circa 1945-1946, 1 folders (Box 9)
    - U.S. Congress. Army Appropriations Committee
      - Formal (Box 9)
      - Informal (Box 9)
    - West Point visit 1944 (Box 9)
    - Youth (Box 9)
  - Postcards (largely World War I era) (Box 9)
  - Postcard booklets (largely World War I era of French views) (Box 9)
  - Films
    - "Round the World Trip" film of Appropriations Subcommittee visit to U.S. installations. 1945, 851419-1-1
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:31:40
        [Restricted]
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851419-1-1, flash-flv
    - "Round the World Trip" film of Appropriations Subcommittee visit to U.S. installations. 1945, 851419-2-2
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:19:26
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851419-2-2, flash-flv
Selective Index to Correspondence
Adams, James Truslow, 1878-1949.
July 14, 1937
Baer, Max A.
June 2, 1945, July 11, 1945
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
Nov. 20, 1928, Dec. 31, 1929, Jan. 4, 1930, Mar. 3, 1931
Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966.
Feb. 23, 1950
Carlson, Frank, 1893-
Feb. 11, 1947
Connally, Tom, 1877-1963
Mar. 27, 1947
Curwood, James Oliver, 1878-1927
Dec. 24, 1926
Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943
June 12, 1929, Mar. 2, 1931, Aug. 21, 1940, Oct. 15, 1940, Jan. 28, 1942
Disney, Walt, 1901-1966
Mar. 21, 1940
Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982
Apr. 9, 1948
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939
Dec. 10, 1929, Feb. 18, 1931, Feb. 7, 1934, Feb. 2, 1935
Forrestal, James, 1892-1949.
Apr. 30, 1946, Apr. 15, 1947, June 9, 1947, June 12, 1947, June 26, 1947, July 22, 1947, Nov. 26, 1947, Dec. 2, 1947, Apr. 7, 1948
Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936
July 12, 1927, Dec. 9, 1935
Groesbeck, Alexander J. 1873-1953
Apr. 12, 1922, Jan. 29, 1934, Feb. 20, 1934
Hannah, John A., 1902-
Mar. 15, 1949
Hare, James M., 1910-
May 8, 1959
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964
Oct. 18, 1928, Oct. 8, 1945
Hoover, J. Edgar, (John Edgar), 1895-1972
Dec. 17, 1937, Apr. 24, 1940, Jan. 27, 1941
Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.
Oct. 28, 1937, Jan. 17, 1938, June 5, 1940
Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971
Nov. 23, 1940, Feb. 3, 1944, Aug. 29, 1944, Dec. 1, 1944, Sept. 3, 1946, Sept. 21, 1951
Knox, Frank, 1874-1944
Apr. 19, 1938
Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987
July 12, 1943
Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969
July 18, 1939, Jan. 10, 1940
Lubin, Isador, 1896-
Jan. 10, 1940
McLaughlin, James Campbell, 1858-1932
Mar. 3, 1920, Feb. 13, 1932, Feb. 23, 1920, Mar. 6, 1920, Apr. 9, 1920, Feb. 23, 1920, Apr. 10, 1922, Feb. 11, 1930, Feb. 11, 1932, Sept. 14, 1932, Oct. 17, 1932
Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959
Dec. 5, 1939, Nov. 8, 1940, Sept. 7, 1944
Martin, Joseph William, 1884-1968.
July 19, 1939, July 24, 1944, Aug. 7, 1939, Aug. 4, 1943, July 24, 1944
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949
July 16, 1937
Murray, Philip, 1886-1952
Apr. 27, 1950
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-
Nov. 7, 1939, Feb. 23, 1944
Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988.
Feb. 23, 1944
Patterson, Robert Porter, 1891-1952
Sept. 23, 1944, Apr. 5, 1945, Sept. 10, 1945, Nov. 5, 1945, June 11, 1947, June 13, 1947, June 17, 1947, July 1, 1947, Section of War
Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965
Nov. 23, 1944
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-1968
Aug. 3, 1939
Powers, Perry Francis, 1857-1945
May 20, 1920, July 16, 1936
Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-
Nov. 23, 1929, May 12, 1931, Oct. 9, 1933, June 5, 1937
Sigler, Kim, 1894
Nov. 19, 1946
Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959
June 24, 1931
Sparks, Frank Melville, 1877-
Feb. 27, 1928, Mar. 17, 1928, Mar. 23, 1928, June 19, 1928, July 11, 1928, July 30, 1928
Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1867-1950
Oct. 1, 1940, Oct. 14, 1940, Jan. 11, 1941, Feb. 19, 1945, Mar. 21, 1944, Feb. 15, 1945, Feb. 23, 1945
Symington, Stuart, 1901-
Sept. 18, 1947, June 26, 1948, Apr. 31, 1948, Jan. 22, 1948, May 18, 1948
Thompson, Ruth, 1887-1970
July 20, 1954
Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924
Oct. 22, 1921, Feb. 7, 1922, Oct. 18, 1922, Nov. 8, 1922
Townsend, Francis E. (Francis Everett), 1867-1960
Feb. 17, 1940
Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972
Sept. 13, 1949
Tunney, James Joseph, 1897-
May 28, 1938, June 9, 1938
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951
Mar. 31, 1928, June 10, 1937, Mar. 31, 1938, Apr. 2, 1928, June 3, 1938, Dec. 17, 1937, Jan. 10, 1935, Jan. 17, 1945
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Sept. 21, 1942, Sept. 24, 1945
Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1883-1953
May 17, 1948
Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965
undated, Feb. 26, 1940, June 26, 1945
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
Sept. 13, 1949, Oct. 11, 1949
Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944
Dec. 22, 1941, Dec. 6, 1940, Sept. 9, 1940